<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse, or parly, continued betwixt Partricius and Peregrine (upon their landing in France) touching the civill wars of England and Ireland.</title>
            <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E61_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E61[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse, or parly, continued betwixt Partricius and Peregrine (upon their landing in France) touching the civill wars of England and Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Howell, James, 1594?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to James Howell.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: Pi B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy has a blank preliminary leaf. On the recto in MS: verse quatrain, and in another hand, an attribution to James Howell.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on first page of text of Thomason copy: "by James Howell 21 July 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:111198:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111198:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111198:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE, or PARLY, continued betwixt <hi>Partricius</hi> and <hi>Peregrine</hi> (upon their landing in <hi>France</hi>) touching the civill Wars of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peregrine.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Sir, you are happily arrived on this ſhore; we are now upon firme ground, upon the faire <hi>Continent</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> we are not circumſcrib'd or coopt up within the narrow bounds of a rheumatick <hi>Iſland;</hi> we have all <hi>Europe</hi> before us. Truely I am not a little glad to have ſhaken hands with that tumbling Element the <hi>Sea;</hi> And for <hi>England,</hi> I never intend to ſee her againe, unleſſe it be in a <hi>Map;</hi> nay, <hi>In ſtatu quo nunc,</hi> while this <hi>Faction</hi> reignes, had I left one eye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me, I ſhould hardly returne thither to fetch it; therefore if I be miſſing at any time, never looke for me there. There is an old Proverb, <hi>From a blacke German, a white Italian, a red French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> I may adde one member more, and, <hi>from a Round-headed Engliſhman, The Lord deliver us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Partricius.</speaker>
               <p>I have often croſſed theſe Seas, and I found my ſelfe alwayes pitifully ſicke; I did ever and anone tell what <hi>Wood</hi> the Ship was made of; but in this paſſage I did not feele the leaſt motion or diſtemper in my humors: for, indeed I had no time to thinke on ſickneſſe, I was ſo wholly taken up, and tranſported with ſuch a pleaſing conceit, to have left yonder miſerable <hi>Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>Miſerable <hi>Iſland</hi> indeed; for I thinke there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch a tyrannie exerciſed in any Chriſtian Countrey under
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111198:3"/> Heaven; a tyrannie that extends not onely to the <hi>body,</hi> but the <hi>braine</hi> alſo; not only to mens fortunes and eſtates, but it reaches to their very ſoules and conſciences, by violented new coercive Oaths and Proteſtations, compos'd by Lay-men, inconſiſtent with the liberty of Chriſtians. Never was there a Nation car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away by ſuch a ſtrong ſpirit of deluſion; never was there a poore people ſo purblinded and <hi>Puppified,</hi> if I may ſay ſo, as I finde them to be; ſo that I am at a ſtand with my ſelfe, whether I ſhall <hi>pitie</hi> them more, or <hi>laugh</hi> at them. They not onely kiſſe the ſtone that hurts them, but the hands of them that hurle it; they are come to that paſſive ſtupidity, that they adore their very perſecutors, who from <hi>polling</hi> fall now a ſhaving them, and will flay them at laſt, if they continue this popular reigne. I cannot compare <hi>England,</hi> as the caſe ſtands with her, more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, then to a poore beaſt, ſicke of the ſtaggers, who cannot be cur'd without an inciſion. The Aſtronomers, I remember, affirme that the <hi>Moone</hi> (which predominates over all humid bodies) hath a more powerfull influence o're your <hi>Britiſh</hi> Seas then any other; ſo that according to the obſervation of ſome <hi>Navigators,</hi> they ſwell at a ſpring tide in ſome places, above threeſcore cubits high: I am of opinion, that that inconſtant humorous <hi>Planet,</hi> hath alſo an extraordinany dominion over the <hi>braines</hi> of the Inhabitants; for when they attempt any Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (whereunto all <hi>Inſulary</hi> people are more ſubject then other Citizens of the world which are fixed upon the <hi>Continent</hi>) they ſwell higher, their fancies worke ſtronglier, and ſo commit ſtranger extravagancies then any other: witneſſe theſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous barbariſmes and violences, which have been, and are daily offered to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> (the two grand ſupporters of all States) yea, to humane <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelfe, ſince the beginning of theſe tumults.</p>
               <p>And now, noble Sir, give me leave to render you my humble thanks for that true and ſolid information you pleaſed to give me in <hi>London</hi> of theſe commotions.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111198:3"/>
               <p>During my ſhort ſojourne there, I lighted on divers odde Pamphlets upon the <hi>Seamſtreſſes</hi> ſtalls, whom I wondred to ſee ſelling <hi>Paper</hi> ſheets in lieu of <hi>Holland:</hi> one the one ſide I found the moſt impudent untruths (vouch'd by publike authority) the baſeſt ſcurrillities, and pooreſt gingles of wit, that ever I read in my life; on the other ſide I met with many pieces that had good ſtuffe in them, but gave mee not (being a ſtranger) a full ſatisfaction, they look'd no further then the beginning of this Parliament, and the particular emergences thereof: But you have, by your methodicall relation, ſo perfectly inſtructed and rectified my underſtanding, by bringing mee to the very ſource of theſe diſtempers, and led me all along the ſide of the current by ſo ſtreight a line, that I believe, whoſoever will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the moſt intricate task of penning the ſtory of theſe <hi>vertiginous</hi> times, will find himſelfe not a little beholden to that piece, which, in deed may be term'd a ſhort <hi>Chronicle</hi> rather then a <hi>Relation.</hi> Wee are come now under another clime, and here we may mingle words, and vent our conceptions more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, it being, as matters ſtand, in your Countrey, more ſafe to ſpeake under the <hi>Lilly</hi> then the <hi>Roſe;</hi> wee may here take in, and put out freer ayre; I meane, we may diſcourſe with more liberty: for, <hi>words are nought els but ayre articulated, and coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as it were, into letters and ſyllables.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I deſerve not theſe high expreſſions of your favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cenſure touching that poore piece; but this I will be bold to ſay; That whoſoever doth reade it impartially, will diſcover in the Author the <hi>Genius</hi> of an honeſt Patriot, and a Gentleman. And now me thinks I looke on you unfortunate <hi>Iſland,</hi> as if one did looke upon a Ship toſs'd up and downe in diſtreſſe of wind and weather, by a furious tempeſt, which the more ſhe tugs and wraſtles with the foamie waves of the angry Ocean, the more the fury of the ſtorme encreaſeth, and puts her in danger of ſhipwrack; and you muſt needs thinke, Sir, it would move compaſſion in any heart, to behold a poore Ship
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111198:4"/> in ſuch a deſperate caſe, ſpecially when all his <hi>kindred, friends</hi> and <hi>fortunes;</hi> yea, his <hi>Religion,</hi> the moſt precious Treaſure of all, are aboard of her, and upon point of ſincking. Alas I can contribute nothing now to my poore countrey but my prayers and teares, that it would pleaſe God to allay this tempeſt, and caſt over board thoſe that are the true cauſers of it, and bring the people to the right uſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> againe. It was well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by you, Sir, That there is a Nationall kinde of indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and obliquity of mind that rageth now amongſt our people, and I feare it will be long ere they returne to their old <hi>Engliſh</hi> temper, to that rare loyalty and love which they were uſed to ſhew to their Soveraigne: for all the Principles of Monarchie are quite loſt amongſt us, thoſe ancient and ſacred flowers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diadem are trampled under foot; nay, matters are come to that horrid confuſion, that not onely the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the Crowne, but the foundamentall <hi>Priviledge</hi> of the free-borne ſubject is utterly overthrowne, by thoſe whoſe Predeceſſors were uſed to be the main ſupporters of it. ſo that our King is neceſſitated to put himſelf in Armes for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation not only of his own Regall rights, but of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelfe, which was never ſo invaded and violated in any age, by ſuch cauſleſſe tyrannicall impriſonments, by ſuch unexampled deſtructive taxes; by ſtopping the ordinary proceſſes in Law, and awing all the Courts of Juſtice, by unheard of forced oaths and Aſſociations, and a thouſand other acts, which neither <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, Book caſe</hi> or <hi>Statute</hi> can warrant, whereof, if the King had done but the twentieth part, hee had been cryed up to be the greateſt Tyrant that ever was.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I am an <hi>Alien,</hi> and ſo can ſpeake with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of your Countrey. The ſhort time that I did eate my bread there, I felt the pulſe of the people with as much judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as I could; and I find, that this very word <hi>Parliament</hi> is become a kind of <hi>Idoll</hi> amongſt them, they doe, as it were pin their ſalvation upon't; it is held blaſphemie to ſpeake againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111198:4"/> it. The old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Maxime was: <hi>The King can doe no wrong;</hi> another Nominative caſe is now ſtept in; <hi>That the Parliament can do no wrong,</hi> nor the <hi>King receive any:</hi> And whereas there was uſed to be but one Defender of the <hi>Faith,</hi> there are now ſtarted up amongſt you, I cannot tell how many hundreds of them. And as in the ſacred profeſſion of <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> wee hold, or at leaſtwiſe ſhould hold, That after the <hi>Impoſition</hi> of hands, the Miniſter is inſpired with the Holy Ghoſt in an extraordinary manner for the enabling of him to exerciſe that Divine Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are growne to ſuch a fond conceit of their <hi>Parliament</hi> members, that as ſoone as any is choſen by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd cry of the Common people to ſit within the walls of that Houſe, an inerring ſpirit, a ſpirit of infallibility preſently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth into him (ſo that he is thereby become like the <hi>Pope,</hi> a <hi>Canon animatus</hi>) though ſome of them may haply be ſuch flat and ſimple animals, that they are as fit to be Counſellors there, as <hi>Caligula's</hi> Horſe was to be <hi>Conſull,</hi> as the Hiſtorian tells us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Touching <hi>Parliament,</hi> there breaths not a Subject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Englands</hi> Crowne, who hath a higher eſteeme of it then I, it makes that dainty mixture in our government of <hi>Monarchie, Optimacie</hi> and <hi>Democracy,</hi> betwixt whom, though there be a kind of <hi>co-ordination</hi> of power during the ſitting of <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet the two laſt, which are compoſed of Peers and People, have no power, but what is derived from the firſt, which may be called the ſoul that animates them, and by whoſe authority they meet, conſult and depart: They come there to <hi>propoſe,</hi> not to <hi>impoſe</hi> Lawes; they come not to make Lawes by the ſword; they muſt not be like <hi>Draco's</hi> Lawes, written in blood. Their <hi>King</hi> calls them thither to be his Counſellors, not Controllers; and the Office of Counſell is to adviſe, not to inforce; they come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>intreat,</hi> not to <hi>treat</hi> with their Liege Lord; they come to throw their <hi>Petitions</hi> at his feet, that ſo they may find a way to his heart.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, I have read of high things that our <hi>Parliaments</hi> have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111198:5"/> done, but 'twas either during the nonage and minority of our Kings, when they were under protectorſhip, or when they were abſent in a forraigne war, or in time of confuſion, when there were competitors of the blood-royall for the Crowne, and when the number of both Houſes was compleat and individed; but I never reade of any <hi>Parliament</hi> that did arrogate to it ſelfe ſuch a power <hi>Paramount,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Superlative ſuperintendence,</hi> as to checke the Prerogative of their Soveraigne, to queſtion his <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> voyce, to paſſe things, not onely without, but expreſly againſt his advice and royall command: I never heard of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> that would have their King, being come to the <hi>meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> of his age, to tranſmit his intellectualls, and whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of reaſon to them. I finde ſome <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been ſo modeſt and moderate <hi>(And moderation is the Rudder that ſhould ſteere the courſe of all great Councells)</hi> that they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the agitation and cognizance of ſome ſtate affaires, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly transferring them to their Soveraigne and his privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: a <hi>Parliament man</hi> then, held it to be the <hi>adaequate</hi> object of his duty, to ſtudy the welfare, to redreſſe the grievances, and ſupply the defects of that place for which he ſerved; the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geois</hi> of <hi>Linne</hi> ſtudied to find out ſomething that might advance the trade of <hi>Fiſhing;</hi> he of <hi>Norwich,</hi> what might advantage the making of <hi>Stuffe;</hi> he of <hi>Rye,</hi> what might preſerve their <hi>Harbour</hi> from being choaked up with <hi>Sand;</hi> he of <hi>Taveſton,</hi> what might further the <hi>Manufacture</hi> of <hi>Kerſeyes,</hi> and they thought to have complyed with the <hi>Obligation,</hi> and diſcharged the conſciences of honeſt Patriots, without ſoaring above their reach, and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at randome to treat of univerſals, to bring Religion to their barre, to prie into the <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> the cognizance of the one belonging to the King, and his interne Counſell of State: the other to <hi>Divines,</hi> who, according to the <hi>Etymologie</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> uſe to be ſtill converſant in the exerciſe and ſpeculation of holy and heavenly things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>I am clearely of your opinion in theſe two particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111198:5"/> for, <hi>ſecrecie being the ſoule of policie,</hi> matters of State ſhould be communicated but to few; and touching Religion, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how it may <hi>quadrat</hi> with the calling, and be <hi>homogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to the profeſſion of Laymen, to determine matters of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who, out of their incapacity and unaptneſſe to the worke, being not <hi>pares negotio;</hi> and being carried away by a wilde kind of <hi>Conſcience</hi> without <hi>Science,</hi> like a Ship without a Helme, fall upon dangerous quick-ſands; ſo that whileſt they labour to mend her, they mar her, whilſt they thinke to ſettle her, they confound her, whileſt they plot to prevent the growth of <hi>Poperie,</hi> they pauce the way to bring it in, by conniving at, and countenancing thoſe monſtrous Schiſmes, I obſerved to have crept into your Chruch ſince the <hi>reigne</hi> of this <hi>Parliament:</hi> ſo that one may juſtly ſay, Theſe your <hi>Reformers</hi> are but the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners of the old project of the Jeſuits, the main part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was, and is ſtill, to hurle the ball of diſcord, and hatch new opinions ſtill 'twixt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to make fractions and ſciſſures betweene them, and ſo render their Religion more deſpicable and ridiculous.</p>
               <p>But me thinks, matters are come to a ſtrange paſſe with you in <hi>England,</hi> that the <hi>Iudges</hi> cannot be truſted with the <hi>Law,</hi> nor the <hi>Prelats</hi> with the <hi>Goſpell;</hi> whereas from all times, out of their long experience and yeeres, theſe two degrees were of men uſed to be reverenced for the chiefe <hi>Ttruch-men,</hi> and unqueſtionable <hi>Expoſitors</hi> of both, which another power ſeemes now to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to it ſelfe, as the inerring <hi>Oracle</hi> of both: but I pray God that theſe grand <hi>Refiners</hi> of Religion, prove not <hi>Quackſalvers</hi> at laſt; that theſe upſtart <hi>Polititians</hi> prove not <hi>Impoſtors:</hi> for I have heard of ſome things they have done, that if <hi>Machiavell</hi> himſelfe were alive, he would be reputed a Saint in compariſon of them. The <hi>Roman</hi> ten, and <hi>Athenian</hi> thirty, were Babies to theſe; nay, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition, and the <hi>Bloet-Rade</hi> (that Councell of blood) which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> erected in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> when he ſwore, <hi>That hee would drowne the Hollanders in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111198:6"/> their Butter-tubs,</hi> was nothing to this; when I conſider the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious power they have aſſumed to themſelves, and doe daily exerciſe over the bodies, the eſtates and ſoules of men.</p>
               <p>In your former Diſcourſe you told me, that amongſt multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of other miſchiefs, which this new Faction hath wrought, they have put <hi>diviſion</hi> twixt all ſorts and ſexes, twixt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, both of men and women; one thing more I may ſay they have done in this kind: for, they have laboured to put <hi>diviſion</hi> between the <hi>Perſons</hi> of the holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> by making the firſt <hi>Perſon</hi> to be offended at that voluntary <hi>genuflexion</hi> and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which hath been from all times practiſed in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church to the name of the ſecond <hi>Perſon;</hi> ſo that <hi>Ieſu-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> as I have read in ſome of your profane Pamphlets, is growne now to be a word of reproach amongſt you.</p>
               <p>But to the point; there is one thing I can never ceaſe to wonder at: that whereras at the beginning of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> there were as able and experienced, as ſtout and well ſpoken Gentlemen, as any in the whole Kingdome, that ſate in the Houſe, and made the far major part, I wonder I ſay, that they would ſuffer this giddy-headed Faction to carry all before them in that violent manner, that they did not cruſh this <hi>Cocatrice</hi> in the ſhell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, Sir, you know there is nothing ſo agreeable to the nature of man, as <hi>noveltie;</hi> and in the conduct of humane affaires, it is alwayes ſeene, that when any new deſigne or facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is afoot, the Projectors are commonly more pragmaticall and ſedulous upon the worke; they lie centinell to watch all advantages, the Sand of their braines is alwayes running this hath cauſed, this upſtart Faction, to ſticke ſtill cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and continue marvellouſly conſtant to their ends; they have been uſed to tyre and out-faſt, to weary and out-watch the moderate and well-minded Gentlemen; ſometimes till after midnight, by clancular and nocturnall ſittings; ſo that as his Majeſtie ſayes in one of his Declarations, moſt of their Votes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111198:6"/> may be ſaid to be nought elſe, but <hi>Verdicts of a ſtarv'd Iury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another reaſon is, That they countenanced the flocking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the promiſcuous rabble from <hi>London,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the two ſeverall motions the Lords made unto them, that they might be ſuppreſſed by Parliamentary Order: This rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crue awed the wonted freedome of ſpeech in both Houſes, cryed up the names, and confronted many of their Members: yet theſe new Polititians not onely conniv'd at them, but call'd them their <hi>friends;</hi> and ſo they might well enough, or rather their <hi>Champions;</hi> for they had ordered the matter ſo, that they were ſure to have them ready at their devotion, at the heaving of a finger: and from this tumultuous <hi>mongrell crue,</hi> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived their firſt encouragements to doe ſuch high prodigious inſolencies they have committed ſince. Adde hereunto, that they complyed exceedingly beſides with the Common <hi>Councell</hi> of the City, they uſed to attend them earely and late, and knock heads together; and if any new thing was to paſſe in the Houſe, they would firſt wait on <hi>them,</hi> to know their pleaſure, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards it ſhould be propunded and put to <hi>Vote</hi> in the Houſe: And how derogatory it is to the high <hi>Law-making councell,</hi> to make their chiefeſt Members wait from time to time on the Magiſtrates of <hi>the City,</hi> who in former times were uſed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them upon all occaſions in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> I am aſhamed to thinke on; nor am I leſſe aſhamed to remember thoſe baſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices</hi> and indirect courſes that were practis'd at the election of this pretended <hi>Major;</hi> here they tack'd about to a ſecond choyce after the the firſt was legally made, and how the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Councell</hi> was pack'd up of the arrandeſt <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> up and downe the <hi>City.</hi> And to that mutinous wealth-ſwolne City, and the ſaid unbridled packe of <hi>Oppidans</hi> (ſeconded afterwards by the Countrey clownes) who offered ſuch outrages to <hi>Gods Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Kings houſe,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament houſe,</hi> may be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all our miſeries, and the miſcarriage of things: for they cauſed his Majeſty to forſake his owne ſtanding palace, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111198:7"/> himſelfe from his <hi>Parliament,</hi> and make that unuſuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe up and downe his Kingdome ever ſince, it put all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at a ſtand, and in a confuſion: But becauſe the buſineſſe may take better impreſſion in you for the further illuſtration of it, I will relate unto you an old <hi>Egyptian</hi> Fable which comes pat to this purpoſe:</p>
               <q>Upon a time, the Starres complained to <hi>Apollo,</hi> that hee diſplayed his beames too much upon ſome malignant Planets; That the <hi>Moone</hi> had too great a ſhare of his influence, and that he was carryed away too much by her motion: They complained alſo, that the conſtellation of <hi>Libra</hi> (which holds the ballance of Iuſtice) had but a dim light, and that the <hi>Aſtrean</hi> Court was growne altogether deſtructive with divers other grievances. <hi>Apollo</hi> hereupon, commanded <hi>Mercury</hi> to ſummon a generall Synod, where ſome out of every Aſteriſme throughout the whole Firmament were to meet; <hi>Apollo</hi> told them, I am placed here by the finger of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be Monarch of the Skie, to be the meaſurer of Time, and I goe upon his errand round about the world every foure and twenty houres: I am alſo the Fountaine of heat and light, which, though I uſe to diſpence and difo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe in equall proportions throughout the whole univerſe; yet I make dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference twixt objects, a Caſtle hath more of my light then a Cottage, and the Cedar hath more of me then the Shrub: But touching the <hi>Moone,</hi> (the ſecond great Luminary) I would have you know, that ſhe is deareſt unto me, therefore let none repine that I cheriſh her with my beames, and confer more light on her, then upon any other. Touching the malignant Planets, or any other Star, of what magnitude ſoever, that moves not in a regular motion, or hath runne any excentrique exorbitant courſe, or that would have made me to move out of the <hi>Zodiak,</hi> I put them over unto you, that upon due examination, and proofe, they may be <hi>unſphear'd,</hi> or extinguiſhed. But I would have this done with moderation; I would have you to k epe as neere as you can between the <hi>Tropiques</hi> and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Zones:</hi> I would have things reduced to their true principles, <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not ruin'd;</hi> I would not have the whole government of the Skie overturned for redreſſe of a few petty abuſes; I would have the ſpirit of malice and lying, the ſpirit of partiality and injuſtice, the ſpirit of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and rigor, the baſe ſpirit of feare and jealouſie to be far from this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Synod; I would have all private intereſts reflecting upon revenge or profit, to be utterly baniſhed hence: moreover, I would not have you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111198:7"/> to make grievances, where no grievances are, or dangers, where no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are, I would have no creation of dangers; I would have you to huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band time as parſimoniouſly as you can, leſt by keeping too long together, and amuſing the world with ſuch tedious hopes of redreſſe of grievances, you prove your ſelves the greateſt grievance at laſt, and ſo from <hi>Starres,</hi> become <hi>Comets:</hi> Laſtly, I would have you to be very cautious how you tamper with my Soveraigne power, and chop Logick with mee in that point; you know what became of <hi>Him,</hi> who once preſumed to meddle with my Chariot: Hereupon the whole hoſt of Heaven being <hi>conſtellated</hi> thus into one great Body, fell to a ſerious deliberation of things; and <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelfe continued his preſence, and ſate amongſt them in his full luſtre, but in the meane time, whileſt they were in the middeſt of their conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the leſſer ſort of the mongrell Starres which make up the <hi>Galaxia</hi> (the milkie way in Heaven) gather in a tumultuous diſorderly manner about the body of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and commit many ſtrange inſolencies, which cauſed <hi>Apollo</hi> (taking young <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> with him) to retyre himſelfe, and to withdraw his light from the Synod: ſo all began to be involv'd in a ſtrange kinde of confuſion and obſcurity; they groaped in the darke, not knowing which way to move, or what courſe to take, all things went <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerlike,</hi> retrograde, becauſe the <hi>Sunne</hi> detained his beames from them?</q>
               <p>Such as the <hi>Sun</hi> is in the Firmament, a <hi>Monarch</hi> is in his Kingdome: for, <hi>as the Wiſeſt of men</hi> ſaith, <hi>In the light of the Kings countenance there is life,</hi> and I believe that to be the <hi>morall</hi> of this Aſtrean <hi>Fable.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you a thouſand times for this rare high fetcht <hi>Apologue;</hi> there is nothing illuſtrates things better, or faſteneth them more firmely in the mind, and makes the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them more pleaſing to the fancie, then <hi>Apologues, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes, Allegories</hi> and <hi>Parables:</hi> And now, that you compare a <hi>Monarch</hi> to the <hi>Sunne,</hi> I remember to have read in your ſtory, of a complement that Marſhall <hi>Byron</hi> put upon Q <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who, after a ſplendid audience, where the choyceſt Ladies about the towne were commanded to wait, when ſhee asked him, how he liked her Maids, he anſwered, <hi>Mad me, There is no body able to judge of the light of the</hi> Stars <hi>whileſt the</hi> Sunne <hi>is up.</hi> A handſomer complement then that <hi>Lord</hi> (whom I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to name) who was ſent from his late Majeſty to condole
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111198:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111198:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111198:9"/> the Arch-Duke <hi>Albertus</hi> his death, did put upon the late <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi> at <hi>Bruxel,</hi> who when the <hi>Infania</hi> had made an Apologie, <hi>That ſhe could not entertaine him then, in that high degree that the Ambaſſador of ſo great a King deſerved, it being a time of mourning:</hi> he anſwered, <hi>Madam, This turnes to my advantage; for it were dangerous to looke upon the</hi> Sunne, <hi>unleſſe ſome cloud interpoſed.</hi> Your <hi>Britannick Sun,</hi> though he be now o're-ſet with theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckie clouds, engendred of the vapors of diſtempered braines, and the rotten hearts of many of his owne <hi>meniall</hi> ſervants, who have proved like the ſonnes of <hi>Serviah</hi> unto him, ingratefull monſters, yet is he ſtill in his owne <hi>Orb,</hi> and will, when this foule weather's paſſed, and the ayre cleared a little by <hi>thunder,</hi> ſhine more gloriouſly and powerfully then before, it being a <hi>maxime</hi> of State, That <hi>Rebellion ſuppreſſed, makes a Prince the ſtronger;</hi> And <hi>Rebellion</hi> durſt never yet looke a Prince long in face: for the Majeſtie of Gods anointed, uſeth to dart ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulgent piercing beames, that dazle the eyes of diſloyalty, and ſtrikes her ſtarke blind at laſt. And truly, as you ſay, I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo clearely of opinion, that theſe ingratefull <hi>Londoners,</hi> as they were the <hi>comencers,</hi> ſo have they been the <hi>continuers</hi> and <hi>contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> of this ugly <hi>Rebellion</hi> ever ſince; They ſeeme to have ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forgotten who hath given them the ſword, and by, and from whom they hold their <hi>Charter.</hi> Their <hi>Corporations</hi> are now growne body politicks, and ſo many petty <hi>Republikes</hi> amongſt them; ſo that they begin to ſmell ranke of a <hi>Hanſ-town,</hi> Poore ſimple <hi>Annimals,</hi> how they ſuffer their pockets to be pick'd, their purſes to be cut; how they part with their <hi>vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> every week; how deſperatly they poſt on to <hi>poverty,</hi> and their owne <hi>ruine,</hi> ſuffering themſelves in lieu of <hi>Scarlet-gownes,</hi> to be governed by a rude company of <hi>Red-coats,</hi> who 'twixt <hi>plundring, aſſeſſements,</hi> and <hi>viſits,</hi> will quickly make an end of them. I feare there is ſome formidable judgement of regall revenge hangs over that City; for the anger of a King is like the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a Lyon; and I never read yet of any City that conteſted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111198:9"/> with her Soveraigne, but ſhe ſmarted ſoundly for it at laſt. The preſent caſe of <hi>London</hi> beares a great deale of proportion with that of <hi>Monpellier</hi> here in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeventh's time; for when that towne had refuſed the publiſhing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Kings <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> murthered ſome of his Miniſters and Servants, abuſed the Church, and committed other high acts of inſolencie; the Duke of <hi>Berry</hi> was ſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the towne to obedience, the Duke preſſed them with ſo hard aſiege, that at laſt 600. of the beſt Citizens came forth in proceſſion, bare-headed, and bare-footed, with white wands in their hands, and halters about their necks, to deliver the keys of all the gates to the Duke, but this would not ſerve the turne, for two hundred of them were condemned to the gallies, two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of them were hang'd, and two hundred beheaded, the King ſaying, he offered thoſe as <hi>victimes</hi> for the lives of his ſervants whom they had murthered with the falſe ſword of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>But, Sir, I much marvell how your Church-government, which from all times hath been cryed up to be ſo exact, is ſo ſuddenly tumbled into this confuſion? how your Prelates are fallen under ſo darke a cloud, conſidering that divers of them were renowned through all the Reform'd Churches in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> for their rare learning and pietie? At the <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Dort,</hi> you know, ſome of them aſſiſted, and no exception at all taken at their degree and dignity; how came it to paſſe, that they are now fallen under this Eclypſe, as to be ſo perſecuted, to be puſh'd out of the Houſe of Peers, and hurried into priſon? I pray you be pleaſed to tell me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I remember to have read in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Story, That when the Earle of <hi>Kildare,</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth's time, was brought before the Lord <hi>Deputy</hi> for burning <hi>Caſsiles</hi> Church, he anſwered, <hi>My Lord, I would never have burnt the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I had thought the Biſhop had been in it;</hi> for 'twas not the Church, but the Biſhop I aim'd at. One may ſay ſo of the <hi>Anglican</hi> Church at this preſent, that theſe fierie <hi>Zelots,</hi> theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111198:10"/> vaporing <hi>Scioliſts</hi> of the times are ſo furiouſly enraged againſt this holy <hi>Primitive</hi> order: ſome out of <hi>Envie,</hi> ſome out of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> ſome out of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that one may ſay, our Church had not been thus ſet on fire, unleſſe the Biſhops had been in't. I grant there was never yet any Profeſſion made up of men, but there were ſome bad; we are not Angels upon earth; there was a <hi>Iudas</hi> amongſt the firſt dozen of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> though Apoſtles, and they by our <hi>Saviour's</hi> owne election: Amongſt our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, peradventure (for I know of no accuſation fram'd againſt them yet) ſome might be faultie, and wanting moderation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not contented to walk upon the battlements of the Church, but they muſt put themſelves upon ſtilts; but if a golden chaine hath happily a copper linke, two or three, will you therefore breake and throw away the whole chaine. If a few <hi>Shooe-makers</hi> (I confeſſe the compariſon is too homely, but I had it of a <hi>Scots</hi> Doctor) ſell Calfes skin for Neats leather, muſt the <hi>Gentle-Craft</hi> be therefore utterly extinguiſh'd, and muſt wee goe barefoot therefore? Let the perſons ſuffer in the Name of God, and not the holy Order of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> But becauſe you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be further informed of the procedures againſt Biſhops, I will relate unto you another Apologue which principally glaunceth at this ſubject:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Upon a time the <hi>Birds</hi> met in Councell, for redreſſe of ſome extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies that had <hi>flowne</hi> into the <hi>volatill</hi> Empire; Nor was it the firſt time that <hi>Birds</hi> met thus; for the <hi>Phrygian Fabler</hi> tells us of divers meetings of theirs: And after him we reade that <hi>Apolonius Thyanent,</hi> undertook the interpretation of their language, and to be their <hi>Dragoman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They thus aſſembled in one great <hi>Covie</hi> by the call of the <hi>Eagle</hi> their unqueſtioned hereditary King, and by vertue of his royall authority. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints were brought, that divers <hi>Cormorants</hi> and <hi>Harpies,</hi> with other <hi>Birds</hi> of prey, had got in amongſt them, who did much annoy and invade the publique liberty: ſundrie other <hi>Birds</hi> were queſtioned, which cauſed <hi>ſome</hi> to take a timely flight into another ayre.</p>
                  <p>As they were thus conſulting for advancement of the common good,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111198:10"/> many <hi>Rookes, Horne-Owles</hi> and <hi>Sea-guls</hi> flock'd together,<note place="margin">Citizens, Sea-men.</note> and fluttered about the place they were aſſembled in, where they kept a hideous noyſe, and committed many outrages, and nothing could ſatisfie them, but the <hi>Griffons</hi> head,<note place="margin">Ear. <hi>Straff.</hi> Creſt.</note> which was therefore chopt off and offered up as a ſacrifice to make them leave their <hi>chattering,</hi> and appeaſe their fury for the time.</p>
                  <p>They fell foule afterwards upon the <hi>Pies,</hi> who were uſed to be much reverenced, and to ſit upon the higheſt <hi>pearch</hi> in that great Aſſembly: they called them Idolatrous and inauſpicious <hi>Birds,</hi> they hated their mixt colour, repined at their long traine, they tore their white feathers, and were ready to peck out their eyes: they did what they could to put them in <hi>Owles</hi> feathers, to make them the more hated, and to be ſtar'd and hooted at whereſoever they paſſed. The <hi>Pies</hi> being thus ſcar'd, preſented a Petition to the royall <hi>Eagle,</hi> and to this his great Counſell, that they might be ſecured to repaire ſafely thither to ſit and conſult, according to the ancient Lawes of the <hi>Volatill</hi> Empire continued ſo many ages without controllment or queſtion: in which Petition they inſerted a <hi>Proteſt</hi> or <hi>Caveat,</hi> that no publike Act paſſe ſhould in the interim. This Supplication, both for matter and forme, was excepted againſt, and cryed up to be high Treaſon, ſpecially that indefinite <hi>Proteſt</hi> they had made, that no Act what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhould be of any validity without them, which was alledged to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate frrom the High Law-making power of that great Counſell, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to retard and diſturb the great affaires which were then in agitation: ſo the poore <hi>Pies,</hi> as if by that Petition they had like the <hi>Black-bird</hi> voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Lime to catch themſelves, for <hi>Turdus cacat ſibi malum,</hi> were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly hurried away into a Cage, and after ten long Moneths canvaſſing of the point, they were <hi>unpearch'd,</hi> and rendred for ever uncapable to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Court, they were ſtrucke dumb and voyce-leſſe, and ſuddenly blowne up away thence without any force of <hi>powder,</hi> as once was plotted againſt them. But this was done when a thin number of <hi>Birds</hi> had kept ſtill together, and ſtuck cloſe againſt them, and after that the Bill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them had been once ejected, which they humbly conceived by the ancient order of that Court could not be re-admitted in the ſame Seſſion. They Petitioned from the place they were cooped in, that for heavens ſake, for the honour of that noble Counſell, for truth and juſtice ſake, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as free-borne Deniſons of the ayre Region, as any other <hi>Volatils</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, their charge might be perfected, that ſo they might be brought to a legall triall, and not forced to languiſh in ſuch captivity. They pleaded to have done nothing but what they had precedents for: And touching the <hi>Caveat</hi> they had inſerted, it was a thing uſuall in every inferiour Court
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111198:11"/> of Judicature, and had they then forborne to have done it, they <hi>had berayed their owne neſt,</hi> and done wrong to their ſucceſſors. It was affirmed they had beene members of that Body politique, long before thoſe <hi>lower pearch'd Birds,</hi> who now would caſt them out; and that they had been their beſt friends to introduce them to have any thing to doe in that generall Counſell. they prayed they might not be ſo cruelly uſed, as the <hi>Solan-gooſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Scot.</note> and <hi>Redſhanke</hi> had uſed them, who were not content to <hi>braile</hi> and <hi>clip</hi> their wings onely, but to <hi>ſeare</hi> them ſo that they ſhould never grow againe; to handle them ſo unmercifully, was not the way to make their adverſaries <hi>Birds of Paradiſe:</hi> In fine, they adviſed them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the ſicke <hi>Kite's</hi> mother anſwered him, when he deſired her to pray to the gods for him, <hi>How canſt thou, ſaid ſhe expect any good from the gods, whoſe temples thou haſt ſo often violated?</hi> At laſt, upon the importunity and pitifulneſſe of their Petitions, the accuſation of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> which kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch a noyſe at firſt, being declined againſt them, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed in the morning, but cooped up againe before night: and after the revolution of foure full Moones, they were reſtored againe to a conditionall liberty, under which they remaine till this day.</p>
                  <p>There wants not ſome, who affirme, that in this great Counſell of <hi>Birds.</hi> there were ſome <hi>Decoyes,</hi> (and 'tis well knowne <hi>where Decoyes</hi> were firſt bred) who called in,<note place="margin">Holland.</note> not only theſe mongrell obſtreperous <hi>Birds</hi> from abroad to commit ſuch outrages as were ſpoken of before, but drew after them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many of the greateſt <hi>Birds,</hi> who ſate in that Aſſembly, to follow them whither they liſted: Others, who were of a more <hi>generous</hi> extraction, diſdained to be ſuch <hi>Buzzards,</hi> as to be carried away hood-wincked in that manner, to be <hi>Birds</hi> of their feather. Thus a viſible faction was hatched in this great Counſell; as if the ſaid <hi>Decoyes</hi> had diſgorged and let fall ſome graines of <hi>Hemlock</hi> ſeeds amongst them: Or, as if ſome <hi>Spinturnix,</hi> that fatall incendiary <hi>Bird,</hi> or ſome ill-boding <hi>Scrich-Owle,</hi> which as Stories tell us appeared once at <hi>Rome,</hi> in a famous, though unfortunate great Councell (when there was a ſchiſme in the Pope dome) had appeared alſo here. There wanted not alſo amongst them ſome <hi>Amphibious Birds,</hi> as the <hi>Barnacle,</hi> which is neither Fiſh nor Fowle; and the cunning <hi>Batt,</hi> who ſometimes profeſſeth himſelfe a <hi>Bird,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Mouſe,</hi> I will not ſay there were any <hi>Paphlagonian Birds</hi> amongst them, who are knowne to have <hi>double</hi> hearts: But 'tis certaine that in this confuſion there were ſome malevolent <hi>Birds,</hi> and many of them ſo young, that they were ſcarce <hi>ſledg'd,</hi> who like the <hi>Waſpe</hi> in the Fable, conſpired to fire the <hi>Eagles</hi> neſt; <hi>and a</hi> Waſpe <hi>may ſometimes doe miſchiefe to an</hi> Eagle, <hi>as a</hi> Mouſe <hi>to an</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:111198:11"/> Elephant: Moreover, ſome of theſe high brained <hi>Birds</hi> flew ſo high that they ſeemed to arrogate to themſelves, and exerciſe the royall power of the <hi>Eagle;</hi> but let them take heed, wee know what became of the <hi>Crow</hi> upon the <hi>Ram's</hi> backe, when ſhe thought to imitate the <hi>Eagle:</hi> And it was obſerved, that they were moſt eager to attempt thoſe high inſolencis againſt <hi>Jove's Bird,</hi> who had been ſtarke naked, and as bare as <hi>Cootes,</hi> unleſſe he had feathered them; ſo that the little <hi>Ant</hi> was more gratefull to <hi>Eſops Bire</hi> then thoſe <hi>Birds</hi> were to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> their liege Lord. But the high-borne <hi>Bird</hi> with the two <hi>golden wings,</hi> the noble <hi>Faulcons,</hi> the <hi>Martlets,</hi> the <hi>Rovans,</hi> the <hi>Swan,</hi> the <hi>Chough,</hi> aed all the ancient <hi>Birds</hi> of the <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> remained faithfull and firme to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> and ſcorned to be carried away by ſuch <hi>Decoyes;</hi> As alſo the generous <hi>Oſtriches,</hi> who unleſſe they had had an extraordinary ſtomach, could not have digeſted ſuch <hi>yron</hi> pills as were ofiered them.</p>
                  <p>The foreſaid deſtractions continued ſtill, and increaſed more and more in that generall convention of <hi>Birds;</hi> therefore the <hi>Turle</hi> would ſtay there no longer, there was ſo much <hi>gaull</hi> amongst them: the <hi>Pelican</hi> flew away, he ſaw <hi>piety</hi> ſo vilified; the <hi>Dove</hi> was weary of their company, ſhe found no <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and plaine dealing amongst them: And the <hi>Kings-Fiſher,</hi> the <hi>Halcyon,</hi> (the Embleme of <hi>Pies</hi>) quite forſooke them, hee found ſo much jarring diſſentions and bandings on all ſides; the <hi>Swallow</hi> alſo, who had ſo ancient and honorable a ranke amongst them, got into another ayre, he fore-ſaw the weather was like to be ſo foule: And laſtly, <hi>Philomela,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Volatills,</hi> who was partner of the <hi>Eagle's</hi> neſt, abandoned them quite, and put a Sea 'twixt her and them; nay, the <hi>Eagle</hi> himſelfe withdrew his royall preſence from them; ſo the <hi>Decoyes</hi> afore-ſaid car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all before them, and compoted themſelves by their <hi>Orders</hi> in that highth, as if like the <hi>Lapwing,</hi> every one had a <hi>Crowne</hi> on his head; they ſo enchanted in a manner, all the common ſort of the <hi>Oppidan rurall,</hi> and <hi>Sea-birds,</hi> and infuſed ſuch a credulity into them, that they believed they had an inerring ſpirit, and what came from them, was as true as the <hi>Pentuteuch:</hi> Moreover, it was ſhrewdly ſuſpected, that there was a plot amongst them to let in the <hi>Storke,</hi> who is never ſeen to ſtay long in any <hi>Monarchie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, by this <hi>Ornilogicall Apologue,</hi> you have not onely confirmed, but alſo enriched, and much enlarged my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the knowledge of things. Good Lord, how pitifully were thoſe pore Prelates handled; what a <hi>Tartarian</hi> kind of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111198:12"/> tyrannie it was, to drag twice into priſon twelve grave reverend Biſhops in that manner, <hi>causâ adhuc inaudita,</hi> and afterwards afterwards not to be able to frame as much as an accuſation of <hi>miſdemeanor,</hi> againſt them, much leſſe of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> whereof they were firſt impeach'd with ſuch high clamors: But I conceive it was of purpoſe, to ſet them out of the way, that the new <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> might paſſe things better amongſt the <hi>Peers.</hi> And it ſeemes they brought their worke about; for whileſt nhey were thus <hi>recluſed</hi> and abſent, they were thruſt out of doores, and <hi>ejected</hi> out of their owne proper ancient inheritance, as it were. But would not all this, with thoſe unparalell'd <hi>Bills</hi> of Grace you mentioned in your firſt <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> which had formerly paſſed, ſuffice to beget a good underſtanding, and make them <hi>confide</hi> in their King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>No, but the paſſing of theſe <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> were term'd <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Duty</hi> in his Majeſty; they wet ſo far, that 'twas not ſufficient for him to give up his <hi>Tower,</hi> his <hi>Fleet-Royall,</hi> his <hi>Magazines,</hi> his <hi>Porte,</hi> and <hi>Caſtles</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> but he muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up his <hi>Sword</hi> into their hands, all the <hi>Souldiery</hi> and <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> forces of the Land; nay, he muſt give up his very <hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> unto them; he muſt reſigne his owne <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and with an <hi>implicit Faith</hi> and <hi>blind Obedience,</hi> he muſt believe, who they did, <hi>was to make him glorious;</hi> and if at any time he taxed them, or preſcribed wayes for them to proceed and expedite matters, or if he adviſed them in any thing, they tooke it in a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and 'twas preſently cryed up to be <hi>Breach of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>There is no way in my conceit, to make a King more inglorious, both at home and abroad, then to diſarme him; and to take from him the command and diſpoſing of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> throughout his Kingdome, is directly to diſarme him, and wreſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Sword</hi> out of his hand: and how then can he be term'd <hi>A Defenders</hi> how cand hee defend either himſelfe, or others? tis the onely way to expoſe him to ſcorne and deriſion; truely,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111198:12"/> as I conceive, it was a thing moſt unfit for them to <hi>aske,</hi> or him to <hi>grant:</hi> But I pray Sir, be pleaſed to informe mee further touching this particular.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I find your <hi>Genius</hi> to be delighted with <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> I will goe on to illuſtrate this point unto you that way, I began with the <hi>Heavens,</hi> I then deſcended to the lower <hi>Region</hi> of the <hi>Ayre;</hi> and now I will bring you to the <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Upon a time, The <hi>Flowers</hi> aſſembled, and met in one generall Counſell, by the authority and ſummons of the Soveraigne <hi>Roſe,</hi> their undoubted naturall King, who had taken the <hi>Lilly</hi> for his royall ſpouſe. The dew of Heaven fell plentifully upon this happy conjunction. which made them to <hi>Bourgeon,</hi> to propagate any proſper exceedingly, in ſo much, that the ſweet fragrant <hi>odor</hi> which they did caſt, diffuſed it ſelfe over all the earth. To this meeting came the <hi>Violet,</hi> the <hi>Gilliflower, Roſemary,</hi> the <hi>Tulyp, Lavander</hi> and <hi>Thyme,</hi> the <hi>Cinquefoyle</hi> (though of an <hi>exotique</hi> planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) had an honourable ranke amongst them; and as ſome obſerved, got too much credit with the royall <hi>Roſe.</hi> The <hi>Flowers</hi> of the <hi>field</hi> were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted alſo to the great Counſell: the <hi>Couſlip,</hi> the <hi>Honyſuckle</hi> and <hi>Daiſie</hi> had their Delegates there preſent, to conſult of a Reformation of certaine abuſes which had taken <hi>rooting</hi> in the Common-weales of <hi>Flowers,</hi> and being all under the <hi>Roſe,</hi> they had priviledge to ſpeake of all things with freedome; complaints were made, that much <hi>Cockle Melampod</hi> and <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> with other noxious <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Tares</hi> were crept in amongst them; that the <hi>Poppie</hi> did <hi>pullulat</hi> too much with divers other grievances: The ſucceſſe of this Senat, this great <hi>Bed</hi> or <hi>Poſie</hi> of living <hi>Flowers,</hi> was like to prove very proſperous, but that the <hi>herb Briony, Wormwood, Wolfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, Rue,</hi> and <hi>Hemlocke,</hi> (the emblemes of <hi>Sedition, Malice, Feare, Anbition</hi> and <hi>Jealouſie</hi>) thruſt in amongst them, and much diſtempered their proceedings: Theſe brought in with them the <hi>Bur,</hi> which exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly retarded and intangled all buſineſſes; and it was thought that the <hi>Thiſtle</hi> was too meddling amongst them, which made matters grow to that acrimony and confuſion, as if the <hi>herb Morſus diaboli</hi> had got in amongst them. Amongst many other good-morrowes, they propounded to the <hi>Roſe,</hi> that he ſhould part with his <hi>prickles,</hi> and tranſmit his ſtrength that way to be diſpoſed of by them; the <hi>Roſe</hi> liked not this bold requeſt of theirs, though couched in very ſmooth language, but anſwered, I have hitherto condeſended to every thing you have propounded, much more then any of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111198:13"/> my Predeceſſors did; but touching theſe <hi>prickles,</hi> which God and nature hath given mee, and are inherent in mee and my ſtocke from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though they be but excreſſencies, yet you know they fortifie and arme me, <hi>Armat Spina Roſam,</hi> And by them I protect you and your <hi>rights</hi> from violence; and what protection I pray can there be without ſtrength? therefore I will by no meanes part with them to enfeeble my regall Power, but will retaine them ſtill, and bequeanh them to my Poſterity, which I would be loth to betray in this point; nor doe I much value what that ſilly <hi>infected</hi> Animal, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Bees</hi> tells mee ſometimes, when humming up and downe my leaves, he would buzze this fond beliefe into mee, that it added much to his Majeſty that nature gives him no <hi>ſting</hi> as all other <hi>Bees</hi> have, becauſe hee ſhould rely altogether upon the love and loyalty of his ſubjects. No, I will take warning by the <hi>Eagle,</hi> the King of <hi>Volatills,</hi> and by the <hi>Lyon,</hi> King of <hi>Quadrupedals,</hi> who (as the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> report) when by faire inſinuations the one had parted with his <hi>tallons,</hi> the other with his <hi>teeth</hi> tnd <hi>engles,</hi> wherein their might, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Majeſty conſiſted, grew afterwards contemptible to all creatures, and qute loſt that naturall alleigeance and awe which was due unto mee, the one from all <hi>Birds,</hi> and to the other, from all <hi>Beaſts</hi> of <hi>Field</hi> and <hi>Foreſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>This Fable ſeemes to mee, like a <hi>Noſegay</hi> of fragrant flowers, the matter of it is ſo cloſely put together and made up; but I pray Sir, What ſhould be the reaſon, that they made that extravagant propoſall for mannaging the <hi>Militia</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this land.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>They cry'd out that the Kingdome was upon point of being ruin'd; that it was in the very jawes of deſtruction; that there were forreigne and inland plots againſt it: all which are prov'd long ſince to be nothing elſe but meere <hi>Chymera's;</hi> yet people for the moſt part, continue ſtill groſſely beſotted, that they cannot perceive to this day, that theſe forg'd feares, theſe <hi>Vtopian</hi> plots, thoſe publike <hi>Idea's</hi> were fram'd of purpoſe, that they might take all the martiall power into their hands; that ſo they might without controlement caſt the government of Church and ſtate into what mold they pleaſed, and ingroſſe the chiefeſt offices to themſelves: And from theſe imaginary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible dangers proceeded theſe viſible calamities, and grinding
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111198:13"/> palpable preſſures which hath accompanied this odius warre ever ſince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>Herein me thinks, your <hi>Staſtis</hi> have ſhewne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves politique enough, but not ſo prudent; for <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> though they often agree in the <hi>end,</hi> yet they differ in election of the <hi>meanes</hi> to compaſſe their ends: The one ſerves himſelfe of truth, ſtrength of Reaſon, and integrity, and gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their proceedings; the oteer of fictions, fraudulence, lies, and other ſiniſter meanes; the worke of one is laſting and permanent, the other worke moulders away, and end in infamy; for <hi>fraud</hi> and <hi>froſt</hi> alwayes end <hi>foule.</hi> But how did they requite that moſt rare and high unexampled truſt his Majeſty repoſed in them when he before paſſed that <hi>(totall)</hi> Act of continuance, a greater truſt then ever <hi>Engliſh</hi> put in Parliament. How did they performe their ſolemde promiſe and deepe Proteſtations, to make him the moſt <hi>glorious</hi> (at home and abroad) the <hi>richeſt</hi> and <hi>beſt belovedst</hi> King that ever raigned in that <hi>Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>Herein I muſt confeſſe, I they held very ill correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with him; for the more hee truſted them, the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident they grew of him; and truly, Sir, herein white differs not ſo much from blacke, as their actions have been diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to their words: Touching the firſt promiſe, to make him <hi>glorius;</hi> if to ſuffer a neighboring <hi>Nation</hi> to demand and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine what they pleaſed of him; if to breake capitulation of peace with a great forreigne <hi>Prince</hi> by the <hi>renvoy</hi> of the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> and divers other Acts; if to bring the dregs and riffraffe of the City to domindere before his Court gato, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Proclamations; if to confront him and ſeeke his life by fire and ſword in open field, by open defiance, and putting him upon a defenſive warre; if to vote his Queen a <hi>Traytreſſe,</hi> to ſhoot at her, to way-lay her to deſtroy her, if to hinder the reading of his Proclamations, and the ſleight in of his Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations encloſed in Letters, ſign'd and ſeal'd with his owne hand, for feare they ſhould bring the people to their wits againe; if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111198:14"/> to call them <hi>fetters of gold, divelliſh devices, fraught with doctrines of diviſion, reall miſtakes, abſurd ſuppoſitions,</hi> though never dropt from <hi>Princes</hi> pen, more full, more rationall and ſtrong <hi>ſinewy</hi> expreſſions; if to ſuffer every ſhallow brain'd <hi>Scooliſt</hi> to <hi>preach,</hi> every <hi>Pamphletter</hi> to <hi>print;</hi> every rotten hearted man or woman to <hi>prate</hi> what they pleaſe of him and his Queen; if to ſleight his often acknowledgement, condiſſentions, retractations, pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations of Peace, and proffers of Pardon; if to endeavour to bring him to a kind of ſubmiſſion; if to bar him of the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Domeſtiques,</hi> to abuſe and impriſon his meſſengers, to hang his ſervants for obeying his Commiſſion; if to preferre the ſafety and repute of five ordinary men, before his honoue; and being actually <hi>impeach'd</hi> of Treaſon, to bring them in a kind of triumph to his Houſe; if for ſubjects to <hi>Article, Treat</hi> and <hi>Capitulate</hi> hith him; if to tamper with his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and make him forget the ſolemne ſacramentall oath at his <hi>Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> if to deveſt him of all regall rights, to take from him the election of his ſervants and officers, and bring him backe to a kind of minority; if this be to make a King <hi>glorious,</hi> our King is made glorious enough. Touching the ſecond promiſe to make him the <hi>richeſt</hi> King that ever was; if to denude him of his native rights, to declare that hee hath no property in any thing but by way of truſt, not ſo much property as an <hi>Elect</hi> King; if to take away his cuſtomes of his inheritance; if to take from his Exchequer and Mint; if to thruſt him out of his owne townes, to ſuffer a lowſie Citizen to lie in his beds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his royall Caſtle of <hi>Windſor,</hi> when hee himſelfe would have come thither to lodge; if to enforce him to a defenſive warre, and cauſe him to engage his Jewells and Plate, and plunge him a bottomeleſſe gulph of debt for his neceſſary defence; if to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate his revenue royall, and reduce him to ſuch exigents that he hath ſcarce the ſubſiſtence of an ordinary Gentleman; if this be make a <hi>rich</hi> King, then is our King made ſufficiently rich. Concerning their third promiſe, to make him the <hi>beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovedst</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:111198:14"/> King that ever was; if to call all the aſperſions that poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibly could be deviſed upon his government by publique elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate remonſtrances; if to ſuffer and give Texts to the ſtrongeſt lung'd <hi>Pulpiteers</hi> to poyſon the hearts of his ſubjects, to intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their braines with fumes of forg'd jealouſies, to poſſeſſe them with an opinion, that he is a Papiſt in his heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently hath a deſigne to introduce Popery; if to ſleight his words his promiſes; if to his Aſſeverations, Oaths and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, when he calls heaven and earth to witneſſe, when he deſires no bleſſing otherwiſe to fall upon himſelfe, his wife and children, with other pathetick deep-fetcht expreſſions, that would have made the meaneſt of thoſe millions of Chriſtians which are his veſſals to be believed; if to protect Delinquants, and proclaim'd Traytors againſt him; if to <hi>ſuſcitate, authoriſe,</hi> and <hi>encourage</hi> all ſorts of ſubjects to heave up their hands againſt, and levie armes to <hi>emancipate</hi> themſelves from that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall allegeance, loyalty, and ſubjection, wherein, they and their fore-fathers were ever tied to his royall Progenitors; if to make them ſweare and damne themſelves into a rebellion; if this be to make a King <hi>beloved,</hi> then this <hi>Parliament</hi> hath made King <hi>Charles</hi> the beſt <hi>belovedst</hi> King that ever was in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pereg.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot compare this Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi> more properly then to that in this Kingdome; in King <hi>Iohn's</hi> time, which in our <hi>French Cronicle,</hi> beares to this day the infamous name of <hi>Iaqerie de Beauvoiſin;</hi> Then <hi>Peaſans</hi> then out of a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet of plenty, had growne up to that heighth of inſolenco, that they confronted the <hi>Gentcie,</hi> and gathered in multitudes, and put themſelves in armes to ſuppreſſe them; and this popular tumult never ceaſed till <hi>Charles le Sage</hi> ſuppreſſed it; and it made the Kings of <hi>France</hi> more puiſſant ever ſince: for it much increaſed their <hi>Finances,</hi> in regard that theſe extraordinary taxes which the people impoſed upon themſelves for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the war, hath continued ever ſince a firme revenue to the Crowne; which makes me thinke of a fractious ſpeech of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111198:15"/> the late <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, to them of <hi>Orleans:</hi> for whereas a new impoſition was laid upon them, during the <hi>league</hi> by <hi>Monſeur de la Chaſtre,</hi> who was a great ſtickler in thoſe wars, they petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, that he would be pleaſed to take of that taxe, the King asked them, Who had laid that taxe upon them? they ſaid <hi>Monſ. de la Caſtres,</hi> during the time of the <hi>League,</hi> the King replyed, <hi>Puis que Monſieur de la Chatre vous à ligue qu'il vous deſsligue;</hi> and ſo the ſaid taxe continueth to this day.</p>
               <p>I have obſerved in your Cronicles that it hath been the fate of your Kings to be baffled often by petty companions; as <hi>Iack Stpawe, Wat Tyler, Cade, Warbecke</hi> and <hi>Symnel.</hi> A <hi>Waſpe</hi> may ſometimes doe a ſhrew turne to the <hi>Eagle,</hi> as you ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; your <hi>Iſland</hi> hath been fruitfull for Rebellions, for I thinke there hapned neere upon a <hi>hundred</hi> ſince the laſt Conqueſt, the City of <hi>London,</hi> as I remember, in your Storie hath rebelled ſeven times at leaſt, and forfeited her Charter I know not how often, but ſhe bled ſoundly for it at laſt, and commonly the better your <hi>Princes,</hi> tre worſe your <hi>people</hi> have been, or the caſe ſtands, I ſee no way for the King to eſtabliſh a ſetled peace, the by making a fifth <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of you: and for <hi>London,</hi> there muſt be a way found to prick that tympany of pride wherewith the ſwells.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Patr.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis true, there hath been from time to time many odde Inſurrections in <hi>England,</hi> but our Kings gathered a greater ſtrength out of them, the <hi>inconſtant people are alwayes acceſſary to their miſeries:</hi> Kings Prerogatives are like the Ocean, which as the Civilians tell us, if he loſe in one place, he gets in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Care and Croſſe ride behind Kings, and the ſame they ſay, may be eclypſed awhile, but they will ſhine afterwards with a ſtronger luſtre. Our gracious Soveraigne hath theſe three or foure yeeres paſſed a kind of <hi>Ordeal</hi> or fiery triall; hee hath been <hi>matriculated</hi> and ſerv'd halfe an Appretiſhip in the Schoole of Affliction; I hope God will pleaſe ſhortly to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell the Indenture, and reſtore him to a ſweeter liberty then</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
